Guide to the Fred W. McDarrah Gay Pride Photographs Collection 1964-1993 MSS.193
Fales Library and Special Collections
Fred W. McDarrah Gay Pride Photographs Collection
1964 - 1993
Fales Library and Special Collections
McDarrah, Fred W., 1926-2007
MSS.193
0.3 Linear Feet
The Fred W. McDarrah Gay Pride Photographs Collection contains portraits of iconic gay figures, as well as photos of demonstrations, parades and other events from 1964 to 1993.
Arrangement
The photographs in the Fred McDarrah Collection are arranged chronologically. Three oversize prints are housed in a map case separate from the rest of the items. Work titles and dates are derived from McDarrah's own annotations on each print.
Provenance
The Fred W. McDarrah Gay Pride Photographs Collection was donated to the Fales Library by Fred McDarrah in 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open for research. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical Note
Fred McDarrah was a staff photographer for New York's Village Voice. For many years, his pictures chronicled the people and events of New York's flourishing nightlife and activist communities.
Born in Brooklyn in 1926, McDarrah spent his young adulthood as an Army paratrooper, photographing the U.S. occupation of Japan after World War II. He returned to New York and completed NYU's journalism program in 1954. Starting at the Voice in 1959, McDarrah set out to document the Village scene, capturing iconic images of burgeoning artists, musicians, performers and activists. He published his photos in a number of books over the course of his career.
In his introduction to The Artist's World in Pictures, Thomas B. Hess writes, "McDarrah does not claim his photographs are art. He claims they are a part of truth. ...And they have something to do with justice" (11). McDarrah cared little for the artistic merit of his photographs, applying a journalistic objectivity to his work at all times.
At his death in 2007, McDarrah was still consulting photo editor with the Voice.
Sources:
Fox, Margarit. "Fred W. McDarrah, Photographer, Dies at 81." The New York Times, November 8, 2007.
McDarrah, Fred W. The Artist's World in Pictures. Introduction by Thomas B. Hess. New York: E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., 1961.
Scope and Content
The Fred W. McDarrah Gay Pride Photographs Collection is composed of photographs taken between the years 1964 and 1993, primarily documenting the Gay Rights Movement in America. The collection contains portraits of iconic gay figures, as well as photos of demonstrations, parades and other events.
Black-and-white photographs.; LGBT activism.
- Series I: Photographs
  - Allen Ginsberg, Peter Orlovsky in their East Village Apartment, November 1, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mattachine Society 'Sip-In,' Julius' Bar: John Timmons, Dick Leitch, Craig Rodwell, Randy Wicker, April 21, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Marty Robinson In a Rally In Front of Stonewall, June 27, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - First Gay Pride Demonstration After Stonewall, July 27, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Craig Rodwell, Oscar Wilde Bookstore, October 14, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Craig Rodwell, Oscar Wilde Bookstore [Copy], October 14, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - First Gay Liberation March, June 28, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mattachine Society Marching On Gay Liberation Celebration, June 28, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - First Gay Pride Rally and March, June 28, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Candy Darling (James Slattery) on David Susskind Show, December 7, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gay Pride Celebration, June 27, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Jeanne, Jules, Morty Manford and Sarah Montgomery, Gay Pride March, June 24, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sheridan Square Gay Pride March, June 24, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Street Transvestites Gay Pride March, June 24, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bouquet at Stonewall Doorway, June 30, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Celebration Gay Pride, June 29, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - John Noble, Bishop Robert Clement, Church of the Beloved Disciple, June 29, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Man With Tattoos at Gay Pride Rally, June 29, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Performance Artist Stephen Varble at Rizzoli Bookstore, December 2, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Christopher Street, March 29, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Quentin Crisp, Passing Old Stonewall Inn, June 27, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Support Blind Gays, June 27, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Tattoos, Chains & Leather Celebration, June 27, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - ACT-UP At City Hall, March 28, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Annual Garden Party, Lesbian & Gay Community Center, June 24, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Leather Bikers Wynn Miller, Gary Sechen, June 30, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Support Vaginal Pride Stonewall Anniversary, June 30, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - ACT-UP of Los Angeles at Democratic Convention, N.Y.C., July 15, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Names Project AIDS Memorial Quilt, Washington D.C., October 10, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Names Quilt, Washington D.C., October 10, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Gary Sechen, Wynn Miller, Fredda Rubin, Katia Netto, Domestic Partners, March 1, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Disability Pride Washington Demonstration, April 25, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Gravestone, Sergant Leonard Matlovich, Congressional Cemetary, April 25, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Domestic Partners Jill Johnston, Ingrid Nyeboe, October 27, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Oversize Series I: Photographs
  - Stonewall Inn, June 27, 1969 (Map-case 2F)
    2 prints, mounted on foam core.
  - Stonewall Inn Memorial Mama Jean Devente, June 30, 1974 (Map-case 2F)
    Same image as "Bouquet at Stonewall Doorway", enlarged and with a different title.